Finding Aid for Joseph L. Sax Papers, 1943-2013
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Case Files
  - National Committee Conservation Planning 1994 (Box 19)
  - Western Water Briefing 1994 (Box 19)
  - Western States Water Council 1995 (Box 19)
  - San Juan River Basin-Issues Briefing 1996 (Box 19)
  - Great Lakes 1999 (Box 19)
  - Ontario Surplus Hearing 2000 (Box 19)
  - Dow Chemical 2000 (Box 19)
  - Hawaii Public Trust 2000-2001, 2 folders (Box 20)
  - North Dakota Law Review Article 2001 (Box 20)
  - Philadelphia Dream Garden 2001 (Box 20)
  - San Benito Co. Water Dist. v. Del Piero 2001 (Box 20)
  - Glendale 2002 (Box 20)
  - Water Policy Meeting 2003 (Box 20)
  - Tulare Lake 2003 (Box 20)
  - Southern Nevada Water Authority (Box 21)
    - Memos Vol. 2 2004-2005 (Box 21)
    - Memos Vol 1 2004, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - Memos Vol. 3 2005, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - 2006 (Box 21)
  - Yolo County 2006 (Box 22)
  - Bayview Land Co. v. Mississippi 2006 (Box 22)
  - Relicition Test Permanent 2007 (Box 22)
  - Great Salt Lake 2007 (Box 22)
  - California Cases 2007 (Box 22)
  - North Dakota 2007 (Box 22)
  - Student Assistant Material 2007 (Box 22)
  - Water Line 2007 (Box 22)
  - Michigan Cases 2007 (Box 22)
  - Notes 2007-2008 (Box 22)
  - South Dakota 2008 (Box 22)
  - Artificial Reliction 2008 (Box 22)
  - Sanger Draft Contract 2009 (Box 22)
  - Minutes of the Board of University and School Lands 2012 (Box 22)
  - Environmental Law Foundation. 2010 (Box 22)
  - Edwards Aquifer Authority 2012, 2 folders (Box 22)
  - North Dakota
    - Case 2012 (Box 22)
    - Statutes and Cases Opinions 2012 (Box 22)
    - Pleadings 2012 (Box 22)
    - Text Affidavits 2012 (Box 23)
    - Text of Cited Materials 2012 (Box 23)
    - Appeal 2012-2013 (Box 23)
    - Motion to Certify Question to North Dakota Supreme Court 2012 (Box 23)
    - Brigham v. North Dakota, et. al. 2012-2013 (Box 23)
  - Wisconsin undated (Box 23)
- Teaching Materials
  The Teaching Materials series (1968-2005, 1.5 linear feet) contains syllabi, exam drafts, and notes for various courses Sax taught. There is also digital content relating to his advanced environmental law, water law, and land use courses.
  - Conservation of Natural Resources Seminar 1968 (Box 23)
  - Law 769 1975 (Box 24)
  - Comparative Environmental Law 1975 (Box 24)
  - Law 759 1976, 2 folders (Box 24)
  - Water law 1976 (Box 24)
  - Public Land Seminar 1978 (Box 24)
  - U.S.D.I. Seminar 1978 (Box 24)
  - Environmental Law 1980 (Box 24)
  - Water Law Planning and Policy 1983 (Box 24)
  - Environmental Law 1985 (Box 24)
  - Water Law 1985, 2 folders (Box 24)
  - Environment and Culture (Box 25)
    - 1992 (Box 25)
    - 1993, 2 folders (Box 25)
    - 1997 (Box 25)
  - Public Trust Seminar 1993 (Box 25)
  - Public Land Law Exam 1998 (Box 25)
  - Hawaii Seminar 2005 (Box 25)
  - Various Course Materials 1987-1992
    (Includes syllabi, lecture notes, exams, and assignments for advanced environmental law, water law, and land use planning.)
- Travels and Lectures
  The Travels and Lectures series (1967-2013, 5.5 linear feet) contains programs, lecture notes, and drafts of speeches given during various conferences and lecture series.
  - Joseph Sax Background WUOM Recording 1967 (Box 34)
  - Civil Disobedience The Law Is Never Blind 1968, 2 reels (Box 34)
  - Boston Public Trust Conference 1984 (Box 25)
  - Sleeping Bear Dunes 1985 (Box 25)
  - University of Richmond Law School 1992-1994 (Box 25)
  - Caron Program 1993 (Box 25)
  - Conference of Western Attorneys General 1994 (Box 25)
  - Reno Speech 1994-1995 (Box 25)
  - Earth Day Smithsonian. 1995 (Box 25)
  - Takings Panel 1995 (Box 25)
  - National Governors' Association 1995 (Box 25)
  - Public Lands Speech 1995 (Box 25)
  - B. B. Speeches 1994-1995 (Box 25)
  - National Association of Counties-Georgia 1995 (Box 25)
  - National Conference of State Legislatures-Wisconsin 1995 (Box 25)
  - Environment and Natural Resources Commission 1995 (Box 25)
  - Colorado Water Workshop 1995 (Box 26)
  - Water Resources Council. 1995 (Box 26)
  - CLE International 1995 (Box 26)
  - American University Speech 1995 (Box 26)
  - DC Bar Talk 1995 (Box 26)
  - American University-Takings Provisions 1995 (Box 26)
  - ALI-ABA 1995 (Box 26)
  - California Environmental Law Institute 1995 (Box 26)
  - The McGeorge Distinguished Speakers Series 1995 (Box 26)
  - Boalt Hall 1995 (Box 26)
  - Ft. Lauderdale 1995 (Box 26)
  - Southern California Urban Water Conference 1995 (Box 26)
  - Water Law Training Conference 1995 (Box 26)
  - Moscow 2002 (Box 26)
  - Urban Land Institute, 1995, 2 folders (Box 26)
  - Public Lands Conference, 1995, 2 folders (Box 27)
  - Defenders of Wildlife 1995 (Box 27)
  - University of Utah 1995 (Box 27)
  - Israeli Society for Ecology 1996 (Box 27)
  - CLE International 1996 (Box 27)
  - Wallace Stegner Center Symposium 1996 (Box 27)
  - Southern California Water Committee 1996 (Box 27)
  - Environmental Council colloquium 1996 (Box 27)
  - Pace University 1996 (Box 27)
  - Harvard Club 1996 (Box 27)
  - Dartmouth College 1996 (Box 27)
  - William W. Cook Lectures 1997 (Box 27)
  - Elizabeth Haub Colloquium 1997 (Box 27)
  - Natural Communities Conservation Planning 1997 (Box 27)
  - South Africa Water panel 1997 (Box 27)
  - Wild Panel 1998 (Box 27)
  - University of Colorado 1998 (Box 27)
  - Yosemite 1998 (Box 27)
  - Georgetown University 1998 (Box 28)
  - South Africa Follow-up 1998 (Box 28)
  - Wolves and Human Communities 1998 (Box 28)
  - Babbit Las Vegas Speech 2000 (Box 28)
  - Public Trust Conference 1998 (Box 28)
  - Vertebrae Fossil Legislation 2000 (Box 28)
  - Department of the Interior Water Law Training 2000 (Box 28)
  - Metro Club Library 2000 (Box 28)
  - American Bar Association 2000 (Box 28)
  - Ecology Law Quarterly
    - Banquet 2000 (Box 28)
    - Symposium 2000 (Box 28)
  - Urban Water Institute 2000 (Box 28)
  - Categories, Culture and Property 2001 (Box 28)
  - Managing Risk in Wilderness 2001 (Box 28)
  - American Bar Association Conference 2001 (Box 28)
  - University of California, Berkeley Water Colloquium 2001 (Box 28)
  - The Hastings Center 2001 (Box 28)
  - Transparencies 2001 (Box 28)
  - Hawaii Public Trust 2001 (Box 28)
  - Fossil conference 2001 (Box 28)
  - Wilderness Management Panel 2001 (Box 28)
  - Raley Colorado River Speech 2001 (Box 28)
  - Colorado River Symposium 2002 (Box 28)
  - Peter M. Wege Lecture 2002 (Box 28)
  - Colorado River Water Users Association 2002 (Box 29)
  - Litigating Takings 2002 (Box 29)
  - UNESCO Workshop 2002 (Box 29)
  - Managing Risk in Wilderness 2002 (Box 29)
  - UC Davis 2002 (Box 29)
  - Boalt Brown Bag 2002 (Box 29)
  - Dividing the Waters VII 2002 (Box 29)
  - American Institute for Conservation Annual Meeting 2002 (Box 29)
  - Wege Lecture University of Michigan. 2002 (Box 29)
  - Uncommon Knowledge 2002 (Box 29)
  - Pace University 2002 (Box 29)
  - The Nature Conservatory Meetings 2003 (Box 29)
  - The Barnes Collection 2003 (Box 29)
  - Paris 2003 (Box 29)
  - University of Illinois Frefogle 2003 (Box 29)
  - Florence 2004 (Box 29)
  - Water Education Foundation 2004 (Box 29)
  - Texas Tech 2004 (Box 29)
  - University of Nebraska 2004 (Box 29)
  - Texas Tech Talk 2004 (Box 29)
  - Texas Water Conference 2005 (Box 29)
  - Association of American Law Schools Annual Conference 2005 (Box 29)
  - Colorado State University 2005 (Box 29)
  - University of Michigan 2005 (Box 29)
  - University of Hawaii 2005 (Box 29)
  - Litigating Takings 2006 (Box 29)
  - Michigan Bar Environmental Law Section 2006 (Box 30)
  - IUCN Academy of Environmental Law 2006 (Box 30)
  - Murnau 2006 (Box 30)
  - The Aspen Institute 2007 (Box 30)
  - Association of American Museum Directors 2007 (Box 30)
  - Water Conference Boalt 2007 (Box 30)
  - Artist Endowment Foundations. 2008 (Box 30)
  - Traverse City 2008 (Box 30)
  - The Newkirk Center 2008 (Box 30)
  - The Aspen Institute 2008 (Box 30)
  - Zaragoza Water Tribune 2008 (Box 30)
  - New Zealand 2008 (Box 30)
  - Vermont Takings Conference 2009 (Box 30)
  - Equity Conference 2009 (Box 30)
  - Vermont Law School 2009 (Box 30)
  - Ketchum Idaho 2009 (Box 30)
  - Columbia University 2009 (Box 30)
  - Takings Conference 2011 (Box 30)
  - CFC Judicial Conference 2011 (Box 30)
  - University of Michigan 2011 (Box 30)
  - Aspen Institute 2011 (Box 30)
  - Takings Conference 2012 (Box 30)
  - Johanna Sacro Workshop 2012 (Box 30)
  - Sydney Conference 2012 (Box 30)
  - California Water Law Symposium 2012 (Box 30)
  - Constitutional Law Symposium 2013 (Box 30)
  - Forests undated (Box 30)
- Publications and Research
  The Publications and Research series (1964-2013, 2 linear feet) includes drafts of articles, copies of final published materials, and correspondence relating to publishing rights and contracts. Included is digital content relating to "Is Anyone Minding Stonehenge", "Heritage Preservation as a Public Duty", "Property Rights in the U.S. Supreme Court", and "Repatriation of Cultural Property", as well as other untitled works. Of interest is a draft of Sax's book Playing Darts with a Rembrandt (2001).
  - Public Trust Doctrine and the Civil Rights Bill 1964-1984 (Box 30)
  - Debate in Hutchins Hall and Big Talk in the Big Top 1967 (Box 30)
  - A Report of the Spock-Coffin Trial 1968 (Box 30)
  - Clippings and Awards 1996-2000, 5 folders (Box 31)
  - Panel on Public Water Supplies 1971 (Box 31)
  - Study on Pest-Control Techniques 1972 (Box 31)
  - The Transfer of Water Rights in California 1977 (Box 31)
  - Riparian Water Rights in California 1977 (Box 31)
  - Appropriative Water Rights in California 1977 (Box 31)
  - California Water Rights Law Final Report 1978 (Box 31)
  - Water Law, Planning and Policy 1983 (Box 31)
  - Mountains without Handrails 1983 (Box 31)
  - Legal Pad Notes 1983-1984 (Box 31)
  - Water Law 1985 (Box 31)
  - Why I Teach Water Law 1985 (Box 31)
  - Law Quad Notes 1985 (Box 31)
  - Ecology Law Quarterly 1993 (Box 32)
  - Michigan Law Review 1993 (Box 32)
  - Loyola of Los Angeles Law Review 1993 (Box 32)
  - Constitution Magazine 1993 (Box 32)
  - Historic Water Use 1993 (Box 32)
  - Lucas Article Stanford Law Review 1994 (Box 32)
  - Understanding Transfers 1994 (Box 32)
  - Wrangell-St. Elias National Park 1994 (Box 32)
  - JLS News Clips 1996 (Box 32)
  - Water Rights 1997 (Box 32)
  - Playing Darts with Rembrandt Draft 1998 (Box 32)
  - Cardozo 1998 (Box 32)
  - Rare Books and Manuscripts 2000 (Box 32)
  - Rosenburg Forum Barcelona 2000 (Box 32)
  - Wolves and Human Communities Update 2000 (Box 32)
  - Defenders Article 2000 (Box 32)
  - Washburn Law Journal 2001 (Box 32)
  - Japan Intro 2002 (Box 32)
  - California Law Review 2002 (Box 32)
  - Daily journal 2003 (Box 32)
  - University of Denver Water Law Review 2003 (Box 32)
  - Daily journal 2003 (Box 32)
  - Water Resolution Archives Newsletter 2004 (Box 32)
  - University of Illinois Law Review 2004 (Box 32)
  - APA Newsletter 2004 (Box 32)
  - National Resources Defense Council Deed of Gift 2005 (Box 32)
  - World Heritage Convention Book Proposal 2005 (Box 32)
  - Legal Concepts of Cultural Heritage Property 2005 (Box 32)
  - Preface: Common Law Remedies 2005 (Box 32)
  - Book review: Balkin Culture of Property 2005 (Box 32)
  - Yellowstone to Yukon and Crown of the Continent 2005 (Box 32)
  - Glacier National Park (Box 33)
    - Park Study 2005 (Box 33)
    - General Information 2005 (Box 33)
    - Article 2006 (Box 33)
    - Interview Notes 2006 (Box 33)
    - Notes 2006 (Box 33)
    - Conclusion 2006 (Box 33)
  - Hawaii Law Review 2006 (Box 33)
  - Cultural Property Interview 2006 (Box 33)
  - Canada 2006 (Box 33)
  - Montana Wilderness Bill 2006 (Box 33)
  - Gloria Flora 2006 (Box 33)
  - Prieur Festschrift 2007 (Box 33)
  - Asahi Blue Planet Prize
    - Presentation 2007 (Box 33)
    - Photographs
      (Contains photographs of Sax, his family, and Boalt Hall at the University of California, Berkeley.)
  - Public Policy Institute 2009 (Box 33)
  - Encyclopedia of Environmental Ethics and Philosophy 2009 (Box 33)
  - Stegner Center Salt Lake City 2010 (Box 33)
  - Natural Resources Journal 2010 (Box 33)
  - Jiang Chinese Translation 2010 (Box 33)
  - Vermont Law Review 2012 (Box 33)
  - Michigan Journal of Environmental Law Article 2013 (Box 33)
  - Hastings West-Northwest Journal 2013 (Box 33)
  - Renaissance Italy undated (Box 33)
  - Various Publications and Research 1987-1991
    (Includes drafts, notes, and bibliographies related to "Is Anyone Minding Stonehenge", "Heritage Preservation as a Public Duty", "Repatriations of Cultural Property", and other untitled works.)
Related material
Additional papers of Joseph L. Sax can be found in the American Heritage Center, The University of Wyoming. Finding aid is available online: http://rmoa.unm.edu/docviewer.php?docId=wyu-ah04451.xml